<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Brian Kissell</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Languages of Mathematics and Technology</title>
      <link>/post/the-languages-of-mathematics-and-technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/the-languages-of-mathematics-and-technology/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;As an undergraduate psychology student, I worked with a quantitative psychologist who had a nice analogy that has stuck with me. He spoke about the process of learning a new language. After studying a language for a few years, one may travel to a new area where that language is spoken and be able to somewhat function in that new place. They may have the skills to ask for directions to a restroom, to order their food, and may have even developed a decent vocabulary. However, it is unlikely that this person will have the fluency and skills necessary to communicate with others in a manner that is productive or meaningful. To truly take advantage of a new language, and to gain the skills to express oneself in a proficient manner, it can take a large amount of work and time. However, it can also be tremendously rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This researcher would argue that it can be helpful to think about math as a language. He argued that there were too many within psychology who were only functioning at a basic (purely functional) level, and these people could benefit greatly if they would work to gain a fluency with the language of mathematics. I will add to the analogy by saying that the same could be said about the technological tools that are used within psychology. While most utilize sophisticated technologies for data collection and analysis, I would argue that many researchers within psychology are far from fluent in the language of technology and programming. Many seem content with using technology at a purely functional level, but I believe that for those who really want to explore and understand the targets of their research will need to develop a fluency with the languages of mathematics and technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the past two years, I have found myself drawn away from academic psychology, and instead have decided to enter the world of data-science. For those who are unfamiliar, data science is an interdisciplinary field that attempts to utilize scientific methodologies, statistical techniques, and algorithms – with a strong emphasis on programming, technology, and mathematics – to gain insights into the large array of data that is being made available by technology. I believe that the fields of both data science and psychology have a great deal to teach one another, and I am interested in exploring what those lessons are. As an attempt to begin that exploration, I am beginning a series on lessons that psychologological researchers can learn from data science. Some of the topics that I will explore in this series include lessons on data visualization, web scraping, data cleaning, exploratory data analysis, cross validation, textual analysis, natural linguistic processing, supervised and unsupervised machine learning, time series analysis, survival analysis, file management, database management, deep learning, many programming languages, and more. I look forward to exploring these topics with you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prior Research Studies</title>
      <link>/post/prior-research-studies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/prior-research-studies/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;unpublished-manuscripts&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Unpublished Manuscripts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vohs, K. D., Schmeichel, B. J., Lohmann, S., Gronau, Q.… Kissell, B. L…. Wagenmakers, E.-J., &amp;amp; Albarracín, D. (2019). A preregistered paradigmatic test of the ego depletion effect. Unpublished manuscript, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis MN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B., Gibson, B., Prewett, M., Motyl, M. (2019). A meta-analytic evaluation of biased assimilation and polarization. Unpublished manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B., Gibson, B., Bushman, B. (2019). The influence of overvaluation on narcissism. Unpublished manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B., Gibson, B. (2018). The impact of physical position and prayer on cognitive style. Unpublished manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. (2017). Has Psychology Always Been So Ideologically Biased? A Historical Approach. Unpublished manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Davoli, C. C., Scherr, A. S., Gibson, B. (2019). Profundity, truth, and bullshit: An investigation of the bullshit receptivity scale (BRS). Unpublished manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;data-sets&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Data Sets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B. (2020). Construction of the Perceived Threat to Identity Scale (PTI) . Unpublished raw data. (link to file)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B. (2020). Experimental Evaluation of the Perceived Threat to Identity Scale (PTI) and its Relationship to Conspiracy Ideation, Political Ideology, and Authoritarianism. Unpublished raw data. (link to file)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B. (2020). Trait Moderators of Biased Assimilation and Attitude Polarization. Unpublished raw data. (link to file)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L. (2019). Textual analysis of speeches from leaders of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. Unpublished raw data. (link to file)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B., Prewett, M., Motyl, M. (2019). A meta-analytic evaluation of biased assimilation and polarization. Unpublished raw data. (link to file)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B., Bushman, B. (2019). The influence of overvaluation on narcissism: Study 1. Unpublished raw data. (link to file)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B., Bushman, B. (2019). The influence of overvaluation on narcissism:Study 2. Unpublished raw data. (link to file)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vohs, K. D., Schmeichel, B. J., Lohmann, S., Gronau, Q.… Kissell, B. L…. Wagenmakers, E.-J., &amp;amp; Albarracín, D. (2019). A preregistered paradigmatic test of the ego depletion effect: Kissell dataset. Unpublished raw data. (link to file)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B. (2019). The effect of experimenter presence on ego-depletion. Unpublished raw data. (link to file)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B. (2018). The impact of physical position and prayer on cognitive style. Unpublished raw data. (link to file)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Davoli, C. C., Scherr, A. S., Gibson, B. (2019). Profundity, Truth, and Bullshit: An Investigation of the Bullshit Receptivity Scale (BRS). Unpublished raw data. (link to file)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B. (2019). Religious decline and contemplation on authoritarianism, religious beliefs, evaluative bias, and political beliefs. Unpublished raw data. (link to file).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B. (2019). Religious decline and source of information on authoritarianism, religious belief, evaluative bias, and political beliefs. Unpublished raw data. (link to file).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B. (2019). Religious decline on RWA, ideology, and Trump tweets. Unpublished raw data. (link to file).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B. (2019). The Induction of religious decline through Video Clips on authoritarianism, conservative ideology, and authoritarian behavior. Unpublished raw data. (link to file).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B. (2019). Religious Threat and Writing about Religious Experience on the CRT, NC, and FI. Unpublished raw data. (link to file).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B. (2019). Religious Threat and Writing about Religious Experience on the Bullshit Receptivity Scale (BRS). Unpublished raw data. (link to file).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B. (2019). Religious Threat on Political and Religious Beliefs. Unpublished raw data. (link to file).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B. (2019). Religious Threat on Evaluative Bias and Religious Beliefs. Unpublished raw data. (link to file).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B. (2019). Religious Threat on Christianity/Muslim IAT. Unpublished raw data. (link to file).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B. (2019). Religious Threat on Christianity/Muslim IAT and Religious and Political Beliefs. Unpublished raw data. (link to file).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B. (2019). The Influence of Cellphones on Serial Associative Cognition: Pilot. Unpublished raw data. (link to file).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B. (2019). The Influence of Cellphones on Serial Associative Cognition. Unpublished raw data. (link to file).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B. (2019). The Influence of Mindfulness Meditation on Serial Associative Cognition. Unpublished raw data. (link to file).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L., Gibson, B. (2019). Teaching about the replication crisis: pilot. Unpublished raw data. (link to file).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;conference-presentations&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conference Presentations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L. (2017). The influence of physical position and prayer on cognitive style. The Cognition of Belief. Washington, D.C.: John Templeton Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L. (2018). Has psychology always been so ideologically biased?: A historical argument for ideological diversity. SPSP Annual Convention. Atlanta, GA: Society for Personality and Social Psychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kissell, B. L.; Gibson, B. (2019). Religious Decline, Political Ideology, and Authoritarianism. SCREE Annual Student Research and Creative Endeavors Exhibition. Mount Pleasant, MI: Central Michigan University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
